Finding Aid for Aldred Scott Warthin Papers, 1893-1947
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Aldred Scott Warthin papers 1893-1947 1923-1931
Warthin, Aldred Scott, 1866-1931.
86199 Aa 2
University of Michigan pathologist. Correspondence, primarily with physicians, articles, and other material relating to University of Michigan Medical School and medical practice in general; files relating to his editorship of the Annals of Clinical Medicine; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
3 linear feet
The bulk of this collection came to the library in 1945 and 1948 from the Dept. of Pathology (Donor no. 2108 ) and from Dr. Carl Weller of the Department of Pathology (Donor no. 2487 ). A small accession came from Dr. Thomas Angell Warthin (Donor no. 6236 ), and 1 folder was received from Dr. Thomas Weller in 1996.
The collection is open to research.
Aldred Scott Warthin was a pathologist, teacher, and author of international reputation who served the University of Michigan Medical School as director of the Pathology Laboratory from 1903 until his death in 1931.
Born in Greensburg, Indiana in 1866, as a youth Warthin often accompanied his physician uncle collecting specimens. He also took piano lessons to please his invalid mother and entered the Cincinnati Conservatory of Music, where, in 1887, he was awarded a teacher's diploma. Warthin attended Indiana University, where he pursued his interest in science and received an A.B. degree in 1888. Warthin then entered the University of Michigan Medical School, supporting himself by teaching music lessons and serving as a church organist. In 1891 he was awarded an M.D., followed by a Ph.D. in 1893.
Warthin began his medical career as an assistant and demonstrator in internal medicine at the university. He assumed charge of the pathology laboratory in 1896. He requested all specimens from clinics be sent to him for diagnosis and soon established a close relationship between pathology and clinical medicine. In 1903 he was named director of the lab and professor. From 1893 to 1900 Warthin spent his summers in European pathology laboratories in Vienna, Dresden, and Freiburg.
Subjects of particular interest to Warthin ranged from the problems of tuberculosis to the importance of constitution and heredity in leukemia and hemolymph nodes as well as genetic tendencies to cancer and constitutional aspects of hyperthyroidism. Following World War I he carried on extensive work on the pathology of mustard gas poisoning. He also addressed the social hygiene problems inherent in the spread of venereal diseases at this time. The last twenty years of his life were devoted to the study of the pathology of syphilis particularly involving the heart, aorta, pancreas, adrenals and testes.
Warthin's writings appeared in the form of pathology textbooks and translations, as well as articles in journals and textbooks. From 1924 to 1931 Warthin served as editor of the Annals of Clinical Medicine (later the Annals of Internal Medicine). Among the books he authored is The Physician of the Dance of Death (1931), a work prompted by his interest in books and pictures he collected which depicted the "Dance of Death." This volume and two others, Old Age- The Major Involution (1929) and The Creed of a Biologist (1930), reflected Warthin's thinking on immortality and human nature.
In 1927 he was presented with a special tribute, a "Festschrift" comprised of fifty-eight contributions to medical science from his students and early teachers. Warthin was also awarded the Henry Russel Award in 1929 by the University of Michigan.
At the Race Betterment conference in Battle Creek in 1928, Warthin expressed his controversial views that religion and the concept of forgiveness of sin only served to harm the human race by the continual transmission of social diseases. He also discouraged marrying for romantic love and encouraged those contemplating marriage to check fully into their ancestral backgrounds to avoid the transmittal of inheritable disease to future generations. Warthin believed the only means to physical betterment and long life came through eugenics.
Warthin was prominently involved in professional organizations, serving as the president for many of them. These presidencies included the American Association of Pathologists and Bacteriologists in 1908, International Association of Medical Museums from 1910 to 1913, American Society for Experimental Pathology in 1924, Association of American Physicians in 1924, American Association for Cancer Research in 1928, and the American Association of the History of Medicine, 1930-1931. He served as well as the vice president of the American Association of Physicians from 1925 until his death. He died in Ann Arbor in 1931.
The Aldred Scott Warthin collection documents the growth of pathology as a discipline at the Medical School at the University of Michigan and the professional life of one of the nation's leading pathologists. The papers are divided into five series: Correspondence, Topical Files, Writings, Biographical/Personal, and Annals of Clinical Medicine.
Subjects:
Annals of clinical medicine.; Medicine--Study and teaching--Michigan.; Physicians--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Pathology.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Medical School.; Warthin, Aldred Scott, 1866-1931.; Medicine--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Student housing--1881-1890.; Warthin, Aldred Scott, 1866-1931.
Contributors:
Adami, J. George (John George), 1862-1926.; Beal, Junius E. (Junius Emery), 1860-1942.; Clements, William L. (William Lawrence), 1861-1934.; Flexner, Simon, 1863-1946.; Hektoen, Ludvig, 1863-1951.; Jacobi, A. (Abraham), 1830-1919.; Kellogg, John Harvey, 1852-1943.; Krumbhaar, E. B. (Edward Bell), 1882-1966; Mayo, William James, 1861-1939.; Osler, William, Sir, 1849-1919.; Rous, Peyton, 1879-1970.; Sanford, Arthur Hawley, 1882-1959; Vaughan, Victor C. (Victor Clarence), 1851-1929.; Welch, William Henry, 1850-1934.; Weller, Carl Vernon, 1887-1969
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series (1893-1947) is divided into three subseries: General, Personal, and Miscellaneous. General Correspondence concerns a variety of topics, mainly medical, including discussions of writings, studies, lectures, and clarifications of laboratory procedures. Personal Correspondence contains correspondence reflecting personal and family concerns. Of particular interest are two letters written by Warthin to "Dear Friend" from Vienna in the summers of 1893 and 1894 in which he shares his reactions to life in Vienna and the medical processes of the time. Also included is a folder of correspondence from Sir William Osler, who in many ways was Warthin's mentor. Miscellaneous Correspondence contains correspondence received by Warthin and Dr. Carl Vernon Weller. Weller served on the staff with Warthin and succeeded him as chairman of the Department of Pathology. Some of the correspondence addressed to Weller is written after Warthin's death which accounts for the collection's later dates.
  - General (arranged chronologically) 1896-1939, 8 folders (Box 1)
  - Personal (arranged chronologically)
    - 1923-1929, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Garden Club of Ann Arbor 1929-1930 (Box 1)
    - Osler, Sir William 1899-1919 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Warthin and Carl Weller) 1908-1947 (Box 1)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files series (1896-1930) is divided into five subseries: Associations and Organizations; Medical Museums; Medical Opinions, Advice and Studies; Publications; and University of Michigan. Although the majority of these subseries consists of correspondence, some studies and reports are also included.
  - Associations and Organizations
    The dates of the Associations and Organizations files range from 1923 to 1930 and often reflect Warthin's official duties within the organization as well as his relations with other physicians of a national reputation. The American Association for Cancer Research file includes Warthin's 1928 presidential address and the Association of American Physicians file includes his 1928 address for that organization. Extensive correspondence with Dr. Frank Smithies, prior editor of the Annals of Clinical Medicine, is included in the American College of Physicians file. The Federation of American Societies for Experimental Biology (American Society for Experimental Pathology) contains correspondence with E.B. Krumbhaar in which Warthin expresses his concerns for the profession and its need for new practitioners. The Archives of Pathology contains correspondence with Ludwig Hektoen and the Rockefeller Foundation file contains correspondence with Nobel Prize winner Peyton Rous.
    - American Association for Cancer Research 1925-1930, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - American Association of Pathologists and Bacteriologists 1926-1929 (Box 1)
    - American Association of the History of Medicine 1929-1930 (Box 1)
    - American College of Physicians 1924-1930, 6 folders (Box 1)
    - American Congress on Internal Medicine 1925-1926, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - American Heart Association 1928-1929 (Box 1)
    - American Medical Association 1927-1930 (Box 1)
    - American Social Hygiene Association 1928-1929 (Box 1)
    - Archives of Pathology 1925-1928, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Association for Cancer Research 1926-1927 (Box 1)
    - Association of American Physicians 1923-1930, 3 folders
      - Washington Meeting May 1928 (Box 1)
    - Council on Physical Therapy 1925-1930, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Federation of American Societies for Experimental Biology (American Society for Experimental Pathology) 1924-1928, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - International Physiological Congress 1927-1928 (Box 1)
    - International Society for Medical History 1926-1927 (Box 1)
    - Michigan Tuberculosis Association (Mississippi Valley Tuberculosis Association) 1925-1928 (Box 1)
    - National Research Council 1924-1928
      - Medicolegal Institute 1924-1930 (Box 1)
    - Rockefeller Foundation 1925-1926 (Box 1)
  - Medical Museums
    Interest in pathological specimens and the need for museums are discussed in the Medical Museums subseries (1923-1929).
    - Army Medical Museum 1923-1924 (Box 1)
    - International Association for Medical Museums (Bulletin) 1925-1929 (Box 1)
    - Medical Museum 1923-1924 (Box 1)
  - Medical Opinions, Advice and Studies
    The Medical Opinions, Advice, and Studies (1912-1929) subseries contains correspondence with lay persons and physicians from throughout the country seeking Warthin's advice and opinions on a host of medical questions ranging from procedures to diagnosis. Reports and correspondence regarding particular areas of studies Warthin was involved in are also included.
    - Medical Opinions and Advice 1912-1930, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Bone Sarcoma Registry 1926-1928 (Box 1)
    - Dibothriocephalus latus investigation
      - Correspondence 1927-1929 (Box 1)
      - Reports (Box 1)
    - Dinitrophenal study 1918 (Box 1)
    - Hemolymph node and cardiac anomaly glass plate negatives (Box 1)
    - Koch Treatment 1927 (Box 1)
    - Pernicious Anemia 1924-1926 (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan
    The University of Michigan subseries dates from 1896 to 1930, the greater portion of Warthin's tenure at the university and consists of a wide array of materials. Contained in the Administration records is correspondence with several university presidents and Secretary Shirley W. Smith, as well as a folder of correspondence regarding the Faculty Bibliography and Warthin's disagreement with the policy of excluding interns from the publication.
    - Administration
      - Faculty Bibliography 1925-1929 (Box 2)
      - Secretary Shirley W. Smith 1923-1927 (Box 2)
      - University Presidents 1918-1930 (Box 2)
    - Awards and Memorials
      - Henry Russel Award 1928-1929 (Box 2)
      - Novy Portrait 1929-1930 (Box 2)
      - Vaughan Memorial 1929 (Box 2)
    - Honor Societies
      - Alpha Omega Alpha 1925-1927 (Box 2)
      - Phi Kappa Phi 1926-1927 (Box 2)
    - Medical Library
      The Medical Library material is of particular interest in that it documents the inception of the medical library as a separate entity as well as the crucial role Warthin played in its establishment and development. As chairman of the Medical Library Committee, Warthin was instrumental in the growth of the medical library's collection of medical incunabula and the Haass and Pilcher Collections.
      - 1909-1930, 5 folders (Box 2)
      - Michigan Papyri 1925-1926 (Box 2)
    - Medical School and Hospital
      - Faculty Concerns 1926-1927 (Box 2)
      - Hospital 1927-1930 (Box 2)
    - Pathology Department
      Included in the Pathology Department files are a variety of materials ranging from correspondence to reports, inventories and examinations. Warthin's role as director of the pathology laboratory is documented in the General Correspondence files which often address policy decisions. The Student Recommendations and Concerns file exhibits some of the racial and ethnic biases of the time as well as Warthin's willingness to support his former students.
      - Contributions from the Pathological Laboratory
        - Vol. I 1896-1902 (Box 2)
        - 1928-1930 (Box 2)
      - General Correspondence 1925-1930, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Lectures-Correspondence
        - Extension 1917-1918 (Box 2)
        - Social Hygiene 1917-1918 (Box 2)
      - Pathology Courses and Examinations 1927-1929 (Box 2)
      - Pathology Inventory 1922-1926 (Box 2)
      - Student Recommendations and Concerns 1925-1930 (Box 2)
      - Summer Session 1923-1929 (Box 2)
      - War Activities of Pathology Department 1917-1918 (Box 2)
- Writings
  The Writings series (1909-1931) consists of manuscripts of many of Warthin's publications as well as correspondence with those directly involved in the publication of the various journals for which he wrote. The Publications subseries contains both alphabetical and chronological materials. The Alphabetical files relate to specific publications authored by Warthin in the period from 1916 to 1931. Although primarily correspondence, some abstracts and completed articles are also included. The Chronological files consist primarily of correspondence with various editors and publishers with regard to Warthin's articles and texts. Also included in these materials are three folders of Responses to Publications which further document the respect Warthin had garnered nationally.
  The Manuscripts subseries (1909-1931) also contains both alphabetical and chronological materials. The Alphabetical files contains manuscripts of several of the books and articles Warthin authored. Those included in these files tend to be rather complete. The Chronological files, on the other hand, are often untitled and occasionally incomplete in their contents. Items in the Reprints subseries include a variety of articles appearing in journals.
  - Publications
    - Alphabetical Series
      - American Heart Journal, 1925-1926 (Box 2)
      - American Journal of Roentgenology and Radium Therapy, 1923-1926 (Box 2)
      - Contributions to Medical Science, 1928-1929 (Box 2)
      - The Creed of a Biologist, 1929-1930 (Box 2)
      - Ewing Cancer Number 1929-1930 (Box 2)
      - Journal of the American Medical Association, 1927-1928 (Box 2)
      - Medical and Surgical History of the World War, 1925-1926 (Box 2)
      - C.V. Mosby Co. 1926-1930 (Box 2)
      - Old Age-The Major Involution, 1928-1930 (Box 2)
      - Osler's Modern Medicine (Memorial Volume), 1926 (Box 2)
      - Peerless Engraving and Colortype Co. 1916 (Box 2)
      - Physician of the Dance of Death, 1929-1931 (Box 2)
      - Roentgenotherapy Textbook 1929 (Box 2)
    - Chronological Series
      - 1918-1919 (Box 2)
      - 1924-1930 (Box 2)
      - Forthcoming 1929-1930 (Box 2)
    - Responses to Publications 1918-1927, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Manuscripts
    - Alphabetical Series
      - Creed of a Biologist, 1930 (Box 2)
      - Handbook articles (Box 2)
      - Legends for figures (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
      - Mustard Gas Poisoning 1922-1924 (Box 2)
      - Old Age (Box 2)
      - Physician of the Dance of Death (Box 2)
      - Statistical data and legends (Box 2)
      - Syphilis (Box 2)
      - Venereal Disease (Box 2)
    - Chronological Series
      - 1909-1930, 6 folders (Box 2)
    - Reprints 1911-1931 (Box 2)
- Biographical/Personal
  The Biographical/ Personal series (1893-1936) is comprised of an 1893 diary written while Warthin was en route on his first trip to Vienna. The Tributes file includes resolutions passed in honor of Warthin following his death as well as related correspondence. The bulk of the Clippings file consists of Warthin obituaries and a small number of clippings which appeared prior to his death. Contained in the Photographs are several portraits of Warthin dating from 1898 to 1926.
  - Diary 1893 (Box 2)
  - Tributes
    - Resolutions/Correspondence 1931-1932 (Box 2)
    - Published Reprints 1931-1935 (Box 2)
  - Clippings 1895-1936 (Box 2)
  - Photographs, 1898-1926 (Box 2)
  - House and family photographs and glass plate negatives. (Box 2)
- Annals of Clinical Medicine (later Annals of Internal Medicine)
  The Annal of Clinical Medicine series (1923-1930) begins in 1924 with the transfer of the editorship of the journal to Warthin. Included in the files are correspondence with the publisher as well as with contributors to various issues. Those files with a designation for a specific month include Warthin's contributions as editor, more specifically editorials, reviews, and abstracts. In 1927 the journal changed title to Annals of Internal Medicine.
  - 1923-1924 (Box 3)
  - 1924-1925
    - General Correspondence (Box 3)
    - July-August 1924, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - 1926-1927
    - General Correspondence (Box 3)
    - Monthly files July 1926-June 1927, 12 folders (Box 3)
  - 1927-1928
    - General Correspondence (Box 3)
    - Monthly files July 1927-June 1928, 10 folders (Box 3)
  - 1928-1929
    - General Correspondence (Box 3)
    - Monthly file July 1928-June 1929, 12 folders (Box 3)
  - 1929-1930
    - General Correspondence (Box 3)
    - Minneapolis Clinical Session (Box 3)
    - Monthly files July 1929-June 1930, 12 folders (Box 3)
Selective Index to Correspondents
Adami, J. George (John George), 1862-1926
in Correspondence, General March 29, 1887, April 10, 1897
Beal, Junius Emery, 1860-1942
in Topical Files, University of Michigan, Medical Library Jan. 18, 1926, March 6, 1926
in Correspondence, General Nov. 13, 1918, July 15, 1923
Clements, William L. (William Lawrence), 1861-1934
in Topical Files, University of Michigan, Medical Library Feb. 6, 1926
Flexner, Simon, 1863-1946
in Writings, Publications, Chronological Series June 28, 1918, May 31, 1927
in Topical Files, University of Michigan, Honor Societies, Alpha Omega Alpha April 23, 1926, Feb. 1, 1927
in Correspondence, General April 13, 1897, Oct. 3, 1902
in Topical Files, University of Michigan, Student Recommendations and Concerns Oct. 28, 1929
Hektoen, Ludvig, 1863-1951
in Topical Files, Associations and Organizations, American Medical Association Nov. 1, 1927
in Topical Files, Associations and Organizations, Archives of Pathology Nov. 9, 1925, Nov. 8, 1926, April 4, 1927, May 12, 1927, May 24, 1927, Nov. 9, 1927, Dec. 1, 1927
in Topical Files, Associations and Organizations, National Research Council Dec. 8, 1924, Jan. 8, 1925, May 29, 1925, June 30, 1925
in Topical Files, Associations and Organizations, National Research Council, Medicolegal Institute Nov. 18, 1924, Nov. 29, 1924
in Writings, Publications, Chronological Series Dec. 5, 1924, Sept. 14, 1925, Sept. 18, 1925, Nov. 21, 1925, Feb. 19, 1926, Oct. 11, 1928, Oct. 15, 1928
in Topical Files, Medical Opinions, Advice and Studies, Dibothriocephalus latus investigation March 12, 1928, Dec. 17, 1928, Oct. 15, 1928
in Topical Files, Medical Opinions, Advice and Studies, Pernicious Anemia Oct. 27, 1924
in Correspondence, Personal Dec. 13, 1926
in Correspondence, General, March 5, 1910, March 21, 1910, March 26, 1910, June 18, 1910, Sept. 24, 1910
Jacobi, A. (Abraham), 1830-1919
in Correspondence, General April 17, 1907, June 18, 1908, June 30, 1908
Kellogg, John Harvey, 1852-1943
in Correspondence, General June 13, 1927
Selective Name Index (cont.)
Krumbhaar, E.B. (Edward Bell), 1882-
in Topical Files, Associations and Organizations, American Association of the History of Medicine April 29, 1930
in Topical Files, Associations and Organizations, Federation of American Societies for Experimental Biology Jan 3, 1924, Aug. 24, 1924, Sept. 5, 1924, Oct. 30, 1924, Nov. 18, 1924, Nov. 28, 1924, Dec. 4, 1924, Dec. 10, 1924, Dec. 15, 1924, Dec. 19, 1924, Jan. 8, 1925, Jan. 19, 1925, Jan. 26, 1927, Feb. 26, 1927
in Topical Files, Associations and Organizations, International Society for Medical History March 26, 1927
in Correspondence, General Jan. 14, 1928, May 18, 1928
Mayo, William James, 1861-1939
in Topical Files, University of Michigan, Medical Library Feb. 3, 1926, May 31, 1926
in Correspondence, General Dec. 28, 1925
Osler, William, Sir, 1849-1919
in William Osler Correspondence folder
Rous, Peyton, 1879-1970
in Topical Files, Associations and Organizations, Rockefeller Institute Feb. 2, 1925, Feb. 7, 1925
in Topical Files, Medical Opinions, Advice and Studies, Dinitrophenal Study Oct. 24, 1918, Nov. 13, 1918, Nov. 14, 1918
in Topical Files, University of Michigan, Honor Societies, Alpha Omega Alpha Oct. 28, 1925, Feb. 3, 1926
in Correspondence, Personal Dec. 15, 1924
also in Correspondence, Miscellaneous (Warthin and Weller)
Sanford, Arthur Hawley, 1882-
in Topical Files, Medical Opinions, Advice and Studies, Medical Opinions and Advice Feb. 26, 1924, March 6, 1924
Vaughan, Victor C. (Victor Clarence), 1851-1929
in Writings, Publications, Chronological Series May 23, 1918, July 18, 1918, Nov. 4, 1918
in Topical Files, University of Michigan, Pathology Department, War Activities of Pathology Department March 30, 1918
in Correspondence, Personal Oct. 3, 1925, Oct. 10, 1925, Feb. 3, 1926, May 21, 1926
in Correspondence, Miscellaneous (Warthin and Weller), Jan. 21, 1928
Welch, William Henry, 1850-1934
in Correspondence, General April 10, 1897, Nov. 21, 1900, April 29, 1907, Oct. 16, 1907, April 8, 1908, July 18, 1908, Aug. 29, 1908, March 26, 1917, Aug. 27, 1918
in Correspondence, Miscellaneous (Warthin and Weller), June 21, 1916